<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>O'Keefe Suttles, Jennifer A.</origin>
        <origin>Eagle, Meagan J.</origin>
        <origin>Mann, Adrian G.</origin>
        <origin>Spivak, Amanda</origin>
        <origin>Sanks, Kelly</origin>
        <origin>Roberts, Daniel</origin>
        <origin>Kroeger, Kevin D.</origin>
        <pubdate>20210630</pubdate>
        <title>Collection, analysis, and age-dating of sediment cores from natural and restored salt marshes on Cape Cod, Massachusetts, 2015-16</title>
        <edition>1.0</edition>
        <geoform>Tabulated comma separated text (*.csv) file</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>data release</sername>
          <issue>DOI: 10.5066/P9R154DY</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <othercit>Suggested citation: O'Keefe Suttles, J.A., Eagle, M.J., Mann, A.G., Spivak, A., Sanks, K., Roberts, D., and Kroeger, K.D., 2021, Collection, analysis, and age-dating of sediment cores from natural and restored salt marshes on Cape Cod, Massachusetts, 2015 -2016: U.S. Geological Survey data release,  https://doi.org/10.5066/P9R154DY</othercit>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9R154DY</onlink>
        <onlink>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/60bfb987d34e86b938916dc9</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Nineteen sediment cores were collected from five salt marshes on the northern shore of Cape Cod where previously restricted tidal exchange was restored to part of the marshes. Cores were collected in duplicate from two locations within each marsh complex: one upstream and one downstream from the former tidal restriction (typically caused by an undersized culvert or a berm). The unaltered, natural downstream sites provide a comparison against the historically restricted upstream sites. The sampled cores represent a chronosequence of restoration occurring between 2001–10. Collected cores were up to 168 cm in length with dry bulk density ranging from 0.04 to 2.62 grams per cubic centimeter and carbon content 0.12 % to 48.91 %. Land surface elevation was measured at each site (ranging from 0.484 meters to 1.51 meters relative to NAVD88) to determine the boundaries of each site within current tidal conditions. Gamma counting results for excess lead-210 were used to construct Constant Rate of Supply age models to date individual depth intervals in the core. Additionally, gamma counting results for other radionuclides, particularly cesium-137, gave further insight to evaluate how vertical accretion and carbon burial rates have changed during the past century. Carbon isotopes were measured to evaluate organic matter source.</abstract>
      <purpose>Sediment cores were collected, age dated, and their carbon content measured to determine vertical sediment accretion and carbon burial rates. Site locations were selected to determine how a change in local tidal hydrology affected these rates.</purpose>
      <supplinf>For more information, see the following field activities:
https://cmgds.marine.usgs.gov/fan_info.php?fan=2015-042-FA
https://cmgds.marine.usgs.gov/fan_info.php?fan=2015-043-FA
https://cmgds.marine.usgs.gov/fan_info.php?fan=2015-036-FA
https://cmgds.marine.usgs.gov/fan_info.php?fan=2015-045-FA
https://cmgds.marine.usgs.gov/fan_info.php?fan=2016-016-FA
https://cmgds.marine.usgs.gov/fan_info.php?fan=2016-021-FA
https://cmgds.marine.usgs.gov/fan_info.php?fan=2016-035-FA
https://cmgds.marine.usgs.gov/fan_info.php?fan=2016-036-FA</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <mdattim>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20150603</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20150610</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20150629</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20150707</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20160618</caldate>
          </sngdate>
          <sngdate>
            <caldate>20160719</caldate>
          </sngdate>
        </mdattim>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Ground Condition. These are the dates when the cores were collected.</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-70.669555664063</westbc>
        <eastbc>-69.908752441406</eastbc>
        <northbc>41.941105783816</northbc>
        <southbc>41.510634060621</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>soil chemistry</themekey>
        <themekey>radiometric dating</themekey>
        <themekey>piston coring</themekey>
        <themekey>carbon isotope analysis</themekey>
        <themekey>carbon</themekey>
        <themekey>nitrogen</themekey>
        <themekey>sea-level change</themekey>
        <themekey>sedimentation</themekey>
        <themekey>wetland ecosystems</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
        <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
        <themekey>location</themekey>
        <themekey>elevation</themekey>
        <themekey>oceans</themekey>
        <themekey>environment</themekey>
        <themekey>inlandWaters</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>salt marsh</themekey>
        <themekey>Constant Rate of Supply (CRS) model</themekey>
        <themekey>age model</themekey>
        <themekey>lead-210</themekey>
        <themekey>cesium-137</themekey>
        <themekey>accretion rate</themekey>
        <themekey>carbon burial</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>National Agricultural Library Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>salt marshes</themekey>
        <themekey>wetland soils</themekey>
        <themekey>wetlands</themekey>
        <themekey>ecological restoration</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Metadata Identifier</themekt>
        <themekey>USGS:60bfb987d34e86b938916dc9</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System (GNIS)</placekt>
        <placekey>Cape Cod (606914)</placekey>
        <placekey>Town of Sandwich (618259)</placekey>
        <placekey>Barnstable County (606927)</placekey>
        <placekey>Commonwealth of Massachusetts (606926)</placekey>
        <placekey>United States of America</placekey>
        <placekey>Boat Meadow River (616844)</placekey>
        <placekey>Town of Orleans (618257)</placekey>
        <placekey>Town of Eastham (619414)</placekey>
        <placekey>Dock Creek (616591)</placekey>
        <placekey>Mill Creek (616621)</placekey>
        <placekey>Town of Bourne (619412)</placekey>
        <placekey>Cape Cod Canal (619536)</placekey>
        <placekey>Scusset Beach (616340)</placekey>
        <placekey>Sagamore Beach (617797)</placekey>
        <placekey>Bass Creek (617465)</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Meagan J Eagle</cntper>
          <cntorg>Northeast Region: WOODS HOLE COASTAL and MARINE SCIENCE</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Research Physical Scientist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>384 Woods Hole Road</address>
          <city>Woods Hole</city>
          <state>MA</state>
          <postal>02543</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>508-548-8700 x2280</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>meagle@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <browse>
      <browsen>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/file/get/60bfb987d34e86b938916dc9/?name=CapeCod_Restored_Salt_marsh.jpg</browsen>
      <browsed>Photograph of a tidal salt marsh creek at low tide with a restored tidal restriction/bridge in the background (Bass Creek, Yarmouth, MA).</browsed>
      <browset>JPEG</browset>
    </browse>
    <datacred>Barry Irwin (USGS Geophysicist), Sandra Brosnahan (USGS Physical Scientist), and Jonathan Borden (USGS Electronics Technician) helped with RTK GPS data collection at these study sites.</datacred>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>O’Keefe Suttles, Jennifer A.</origin>
        <origin>Brosnahan, Sandra M.</origin>
        <origin>Gonneea, Meagan E.</origin>
        <origin>Kroeger, Kevin D.</origin>
        <pubdate>2019</pubdate>
        <title>Continuous monitoring data from natural and restored salt marshes on Cape Cod, Massachusetts, 2016-17</title>
        <edition>1.0</edition>
        <geoform>tabular digital data</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>data release</sername>
          <issue>DOI:10.5066/P9YLXOY8</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9YLXOY8</onlink>
        <onlink>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/5da76672e4b09fd3b0c9c134</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Radionuclide detection limits are specific to an individual sample and are a function of: 1) the detector efficiency at the energy level of the peak being measured; 2) the branching ratio (expected fraction of decay events at the energy level), 3) the background activity within the sample. Detector efficiency was determined from EPA standard pitchblende ore in the same geometry as the samples. Activities of 7Be, 137Cs, and excess 210Pb (i.e. unsupported) were decay-corrected to time of collection. Suppression of low energy peaks by self-absorption was corrected for according to Cutshall and others, 1983. Peak detection, with respect to background activity, is calculated for each radionuclide in the APTEC peak integration spectroscopy software during sample analysis. Generally, measured radionuclide activity greater than or equal to 0.270 (210Pb), 0.036 (226Ra), 0.466 (7Be), and 0.003 (137Cs) dpm/g were accepted as above detection limit for this dataset.

Samples were analyzed for carbon and nitrogen content in one of two laboratories. 1) Samples reported with both isotopic signature and weight percent of carbon and nitrogen were analyzed by the University of California - Davis (UC Davis), Stable Isotope Facility (SIF) with an Elementar Vario EL Cube or Micro Cube elemental analyzer interfaced to a PDZ Europa 20-20 isotope ratio mass spectrometer. During analysis, samples were interspersed with several replicates of at least four different laboratory reference material; these reference materials have a long term standard deviation is 0.2 per mil for 13C and 0.3 per mil for 15N. 2) Samples reported with only weight percent of carbon and nitrogen (no istopic signature reported) were analyzed for Total Carbon (TC) and Nitrogen (TN) on a Perkin-Elmer Series II CHNS/O Elemental Analyzer at USGS Woods Hole Coastal and Marine Science Center. A series of calibration blanks and reference standards were analyzed daily.  A standard reference estuarine marine sediment, MESS-2, was analyzed throughout each set of sample runs and was determined to have an average wt%C of 2.10 ± 0.04 and wt%N of 0.17 ± 0.03, compared to published values of 2.14 ± 0.03 and 0.16 respectively. For determination of Organic Carbon (OC) and Nitrogen (ON), samples, along with blanks and standards were placed in a fuming hydrochloric acid desiccator overnight. Fumed Mess-2 was determined to have an average of 1.40 ± 0.08 wt%OC and 0.15 ± 0.01 wt%ON. Triplicate samples had an average relative standard deviation of 6.3 % OC and 5.0 % ON. The detection limit was determined as wt%OC of 0.10 and wt%ON of 0.01. Any analysis value below detection is given the numerical value of 0. Any attribute that was not measured for a specific sample is left as a blank cell.

Cutshall, N.H., Larsen, I.L., and Olsen, C.R., 1983, Direct analysis of 210 Pb in sediment samples—Self-absorption corrections: Nuclear Instruments and Methods in Physics Research, v. 206, issues 1–2, p. 309–312, https://doi.org/10.1016/0167-5087(83)91273-5.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Dataset was queried for maximum and minimum values to be sure sample analyses were within expected ranges for the environmental conditions.  Data were plotted to look for any obvious outliers that may have been indicative of analytical error. Samples with questionable results were re-analyzed. Detection limits are defined in the attribute accuracy section of the metadata. Any analysis value below detection is given the numerical value of 0. For samples that had detectable total 210Pb but 226Ra was below detection, an estimate of 226Ra, based on the measured values throughout the core, was used to create the age-model. Those estimated 226Ra values and their uncertainties are: 0.5000, 0.0000 for core IDs QCNA and QCNB; 0.5000, 0.1000 for core IDs QCRA, BMRA; 0.6000, 0.1000 for core IDs SBNA, SBNB, SBRB, BMRB; 0.4000, 0.1000 for core ID SBRA; 0.7513, 0.0757 for core SMB. Any attribute that was not measured for a specific sample is listed as an empty or blank cell. Each sample was treated in the same manner for each analysis.</logic>
    <complete>The dataset is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. All sample measurements are reported. Note that no samples were analyzed (and no data is reported) for two cores that were collected (QCRB or SMA) because these cores were found to be unusable once brought back for sectioning in the laboratory. Scusset Marsh (SM) is the only site from which a "C" core was collected. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Latitude and Longitude were measured with a handheld Garmin GPSMAP 76Cx unit in the field at time of collection. The GPS unit indicated accuracy was within 3 meters. No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>Land surface elevations were measured by Trimble Real-Time Kinematic (RTK) GPS across the collection area after core collection. Surveyors returned to the core collection sites, navigated to the core collection locations, and surveyed several points. Average vertical accuracy of this method is +/- 5 centimeters. No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted.</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>19 sediment cores were collected in coastal salt marshes in 2015 and 2016. A piston coring system was used, where the PVC core liner (diameter 11 cm, 1-2 m in length) was fitted with a gasketed piston that was placed on the sediment surface. The clear, sharpened core liner was pushed down into the marsh subsurface, while the piston was maintained at the marsh surface via tension on the piston. We visually observed the sediment surface to ensure that the soil column did not compact during collection. Once the core reached the desired depth, the core liner and piston were removed from the marsh with a pulley system. The process date reflects the last occurrence of the work.</procdesc>
        <procdate>2016</procdate>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntper>Meagan J Eagle</cntper>
              <cntorg>Northeast Region: WOODS HOLE COASTAL and MARINE SCIENCE CENTER</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Research Physical Scientist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
              <address>384 Woods Hole Road</address>
              <city>Woods Hole</city>
              <state>MA</state>
              <postal>02543</postal>
              <country>US</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>508-548-8700 x2280</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>meagle@usgs.gov</cntemail>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>At the end of each core collection date, the sediment cores were immediately returned to the USGS Woods Hole Coastal and Marine Science Center. They were placed in a refrigerator for 1 to 3 days, then split vertically, sectioned at 1 or 2 cm intervals, frozen, and then freeze dried for 7 days, until sediment weights did not change further. Dry bulk density was determined as the dry weight of a known volume of sample. Approximately 5 g of dried sediment sample was blended and homogenized prior to sealing in a jar for a minimum of three weeks and then placed on a planar-type gamma counter for 24 to 48 hours to measure 7Be, 137Cs, 210Pb, and 226Ra at 477, 662, 46.5 and 352 kiloelectron volts (KeV) energies, respectively (Canberra Inc., USA). Detector efficiency was determined from EPA standard pitchblende ore in the same geometry as the samples. Excess 210Pb was calculated as the decay-corrected difference between total 210Pb and supported 210Pb (considered to be equal to 226Ra).  Activities of 7Be, 137Cs, and excess 210Pb were decay-corrected to time of collection, using their respective half-lives. Suppression of low energy peaks by self-absorption was corrected for according to Cutshall and others, 1983. Gamma spectroscopy detection limits were determined in APTEC software for each sample; refer to the attribute accuracy section of this metadata for further details. Values reported are above this limit, while values below are reported as 0. Core sections not analyzed are reported as blank cells. Sediment ages and accretion rates were calculated with the Constant Rate of Supply (CRS) excess 210Pb age model, a variant on the advection-decay equation (Appleby and Oldfield, 1978; Goldberg, 1963). This model assumes that 210Pb supply to the sediment surface is constant through time, but allows for changing sedimentation rates, in addition to decay, to control the down-core activity of excess 210Pb. The common form of the CRS model, as derived by Appleby and Oldfield (1978), solves for age based on the distribution of excess 210Pb in the sediment record. Prior to application of the age model, excess 210Pb profiles were evaluated to ensure they were sufficiently resolved to apply the CRS model without bias towards ages that are too old or accretion rates that are too low at depth (Binford, 1990). All gamma analyses were ongoing from 2015 and completed in 2017.

Appleby, P.G., and Oldfield, Frank, 1978, The calculation of lead-210 dates assuming a constant rate of supply of unsupported 210Pb to the sediment: Catena, v. 5, issue 1, p. 1–8, https://doi.org/10.1016/S0341-8162(78)80002-2.

Binford, M.W., 1990, Calculation and uncertainty analysis of 210 Pb dates for PIRLA project lake sediment cores: Journal of Paleolimnology, v. 3, issue 3, p. 253-267, https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00219461.

Cutshall, N.H., Larsen, I.L., and Olsen, C.R., 1983, Direct analysis of 210 Pb in sediment samples—Self-absorption corrections: Nuclear Instruments and Methods in Physics Research, v. 206, issues 1–2, p. 309–312, https://doi.org/10.1016/0167-5087(83)91273-5.

Goldberg, E.D., 1963, Geochronology with 210 Pb, in Miller, J.A., convener, Radioactive dating: International Atomic Energy Agency Symposium on Radioactive Dating, Athens, Greece, November 19-23, 1962, [Proceedings], p. 121-131.</procdesc>
        <procdate>2017</procdate>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntper>Meagan J Eagle</cntper>
              <cntorg>Northeast Region: WOODS HOLE COASTAL and MARINE SCIENCE CENTER</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Research Physical Scientist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
              <address>384 Woods Hole Road</address>
              <city>Woods Hole</city>
              <state>MA</state>
              <postal>02543</postal>
              <country>US</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>508-548-8700 x2280</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>meagle@usgs.gov</cntemail>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>A sub-sample of freeze dried sediment (0.5 g) was ball-milled to a fine powder and packaged for analysis Total Carbon and Nitrogen. Samples were analyzed for carbon and nitrogen content in one of two laboratories. 1) Samples reported with both isotopic signature and weight percent of carbon and nitrogen were analyzed by the University of California - Davis (UC Davis), Stable Isotope Facility (SIF) with an Elementar Vario EL Cube or Micro Cube elemental analyzer interfaced to a PDZ Europa 20-20 isotope ratio mass spectrometer. During analysis, samples were interspersed with several replicates of at least four different laboratory reference material; these reference materials have a long term standard deviation is 0.2 per mil for 13C and 0.3 per mil for 15N. 2) Samples reported with only weight percent of carbon and nitrogen (no isotopic signature reported) were analyzed by the USGS Woods Hole Coastal and Marine Science Center. Sample preparation involved weighing 10-30 micrograms of ball-milled sediment into a silver capsule, sediment was moistened and placed in a fuming hydrochloric acid desiccator overnight. The sample was subsequently dried at 60 degrees Celsius and then encapsulated for carbon and nitrogen analysis via a Perkin Elmer 2400 Series II CHNS/O analyzer. Standards, blanks, and reference sediment with a known carbon and nitrogen content were run to verify results (see attribute accuracy report for further details). Analysis of fumed samples yields organic carbon and nitrogen; analysis of non-fumed samples yields total carbon and nitrogen. These analyses occurred concurrently with analyses in the previous process step; after radionuclide analysis was completed on a core, we would begin the carbon and nitrogen analysis (as other cores were still in the process of being analyzed for radionuclide)</procdesc>
        <procdate>2019</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Raw data was entered into an Excel spreadsheet where all calculations were completed. The Excel spreadsheet was exported as a CSV file from Excel for Mac version 15.33. The CSV file was processed in MATLAB to round calculated values to appropriate place values and again exported as a comma separated text file (*.csv). Note that all calculations were performed prior to rounding and truncating values reported in this data release.</procdesc>
        <procdate>2020</procdate>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntper>Meagan J. Eagle</cntper>
              <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Research Physical Scientist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
              <address>384 Woods Hole Rd.</address>
              <city>Woods Hole</city>
              <state>MA</state>
              <postal>02543</postal>
              <country>United States</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>508-548-8700 x 2280</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>meagle@usgs.gov</cntemail>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>Geographic Names Information System (GNIS) placenames are included as keywords to give the general location of core collections. The entity contains attributes with specific latitude and longitude of each core collection; several attributes are also included to describe the core collection location: nearest body of water, vegetation type, and in some cases, the nearest road. Refer to the entity and attribute definitions for "Site", "Status", and "ID" for details.</indspref>
    <direct>Point</direct>
    <ptvctinf>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>Point</sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt>1075</ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <geograph>
        <latres>1.0E-5</latres>
        <longres>1.0E-5</longres>
        <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
      </geograph>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
    <vertdef>
      <depthsys>
        <depthdn>North American Vertical Datum of 1988 (NAVD88)</depthdn>
        <depthres>0.01</depthres>
        <depthdu>meters</depthdu>
        <depthem>Attribute values</depthem>
      </depthsys>
    </vertdef>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Data_RestoredMarshes_Cores.csv</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Comma separated text file with soil core data collected from natural and restored salt marsh sites Cape Cod, MA. The csv file includes latitude and longitude of core collection, calculated values of soil dry bulk density, mass accumulation rates, vertical accretion rates, and carbon burial rates. Also included are the data required for those calculations: radionuclide data, soil carbon and nitrogen content. The dataset includes 1075 records</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Site</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A text identifier for the general location of the study site.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Quivett</edomv>
            <edomvd>Quivett Creek, Dennis, MA</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Bass</edomv>
            <edomvd>Bass Creek, Yarmouth, MA</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Stony</edomv>
            <edomvd>Stony Brook, Brewster, MA</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Boat</edomv>
            <edomvd>Boat Meadow, Eastham and Orleans, MA</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Scusset</edomv>
            <edomvd>Scusset marsh (restored) and Mill Creek marsh (natural), Sagamore and Sandwich, MA</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Status</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A text identifier indicating whether the core was collected in a natural marsh or a formerly restricted (now restored) marsh.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Natural</edomv>
            <edomvd>Marsh with no history of hydrologic restriction.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Restored</edomv>
            <edomvd>Marsh with history of hydrologic restriciton, now with tidal exchange restored.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Abbreviated alphabetical identification code of each core to indicate: 1) the marsh site from which it was collected (using a two letter abbreviation); 2) the status of the marsh (N for natural, R for Restored); and 3) a qualifier of A, B or C to indicate the order of core collection over time.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>QCNA</edomv>
            <edomvd>Quivett Creek, natural core A</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>QCNB</edomv>
            <edomvd>Quivett Creek, natural core B</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>QCRA</edomv>
            <edomvd>Quivett Creek, restored core A</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>BCNA</edomv>
            <edomvd>Bass Creek, natural core A</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>BCNB</edomv>
            <edomvd>Bass Creek, natural core B</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>BCRA</edomv>
            <edomvd>Bass Creek, restored core A</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>BCRB</edomv>
            <edomvd>Bass Creek, restored core B</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>SBNA</edomv>
            <edomvd>Stony Brook, natural core A</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>SBNB</edomv>
            <edomvd>Stony Brook, natural core B</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>SBRA</edomv>
            <edomvd>Stony Brook, restored core A</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>SBRB</edomv>
            <edomvd>Stony Brook, restored core B</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>BMNA</edomv>
            <edomvd>Boat Meadow, natural core A</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>BMNB</edomv>
            <edomvd>Boat Meadow, natural core B</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>BMRA</edomv>
            <edomvd>Boat Meadow, restored core A</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>BMRB</edomv>
            <edomvd>Boat Meadow, restored core B</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>SMRB</edomv>
            <edomvd>Scussett Marsh, restored core B</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>SMRC</edomv>
            <edomvd>Scussett Marsh, restored core C</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>MCNA</edomv>
            <edomvd>Mill Creek, natural core A</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>MCNB</edomv>
            <edomvd>Mill Creek, natural core B</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Date</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A numeric identifier of the date the core was collected in the format of month/day/year.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>06/03/2015</rdommin>
            <rdommax>07/19/2016</rdommax>
            <attrunit>date: month/day/year</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Lat</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Latitude decimal degrees north, NAD83.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>41.71575</rdommin>
            <rdommax>41.80291</rdommax>
            <attrunit>decimal degrees</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Lon</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Longitude decimal degrees west, NAD83. The negative value indicates a location in the western hemisphere.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-70.51978</rdommin>
            <rdommax>-69.98568</rdommax>
            <attrunit>decimal degrees</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Depth</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A numeric identifier of the interval mid-point depth below the sediment interface in centimeters. Note that depth = 0 cm is given as a reference point in order to include the land surface elevation within the dataset. Sediment core analyses are not reported for this sample depth because it is not a sampled horizon within a collected core. The minimum interval mid-point for each core is 0.5 cm.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>167.0</rdommax>
            <attrunit>centimeters</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Elevation</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A numeric identifier of interval mid-point elevation relative to NAVD88 datum in centimeters. Calculated by subtracting the mid-interval sample depth from the NAVD88 elevation of the core location reported as depth = 0 cm within the dataset for each core.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-118.6</rdommin>
            <rdommax>151.0</rdommax>
            <attrunit>centimeter</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DBD</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Dry Bulk Density: A numeric identifier of the sediment dry bulk density in grams per cubic centimeter (g/cm3). Blank/empty cells indicate the measurement was not done.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.0358</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2.6248</rdommax>
            <attrunit>grams per cubic centimeter</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>210Pb</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A numeric identifier of the sediment total lead-210 activity in decays per minute per gram (dpm/g). Measured at 46.5 kiloelectron volts (KeV) on a planar gamma counter. Blank/empty cells indicate the measurement was not done.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.2709</rdommin>
            <rdommax>34.9084</rdommax>
            <attrunit>decays per minute per gram</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>210Pb_e</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A numeric identifier of the measurement error in sediment total lead-210 activity in decays per minute per gram (dpm/g). Blank/empty cells indicate the measurement was not done.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.0345</rdommin>
            <rdommax>0.9975</rdommax>
            <attrunit>decays per minute per gram</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>226Ra</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A numeric identifier of the sediment total radium-226 activity in decays per minute per gram (dpm/g). Measured at 352 kiloelectron volts (KeV) on a planar gamma counter. Blank/empty cells indicate the measurement was not done. The value 0.00 is given to analyzed samples found to be below detection.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.0360</rdommin>
            <rdommax>3.0504</rdommax>
            <attrunit>decays per minute per gram</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>226Ra_e</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A numeric identifier of the measurement error in sediment total radium-226 activity in decays per minute per gram (dpm/g). Blank/empty cells indicate the measurement was not done. The value 0.00 is given to analyzed samples found to be below detection.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.0098</rdommin>
            <rdommax>0.4011</rdommax>
            <attrunit>decays per minute per gram</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>210Pbex</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A numeric identifier of the sediment excess lead-210 activity in decays per minute per gram (dpm/g), decay-corrected to date of core collection. Calculated as the difference between total lead-210 and total radium-226 activities. Blank/empty cells indicate the measurement was not done.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-0.3410</rdommin>
            <rdommax>34.2095</rdommax>
            <attrunit>decays per minute per gram</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>210Pbex_e</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A numeric identifier of the propagated measurement error in sediment excess lead-210 activity in decays per minute per gram (dpm/g), decay-corrected to date of core collection. Blank/empty cells indicate the measurement was not done.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.0385</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1.0243</rdommax>
            <attrunit>decays per minute per gram</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>137Cs</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A numeric identifier of the sediment total cesium-137 activity in decays per minute per gram (dpm/g), decay-corrected to date of core collection. Measured at 662 kiloelectron volts (KeV) on a planar gamma counter. Blank/empty cells indicate the measurement was not done. The value 0.00 is given to analyzed samples found to be below detection.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.0037</rdommin>
            <rdommax>12.3840</rdommax>
            <attrunit>decays per minute per gram</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>137Cs_e</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A numeric identifier of the measurement error in sediment total cesium-137 activity in decays per minute per gram (dpm/g), decay-corrected to date of core collection. Blank/empty cells indicate the measurement was not done. The value 0.00 is given to analyzed samples found to be below detection.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.0010</rdommin>
            <rdommax>0.9418</rdommax>
            <attrunit>decays per minute per gram</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>7Be</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A numeric identifier of the total sediment beryllium-7 activity in decays per minute per gram (dpm/g), decay corrected to date of core collection. Measured at 477 kiloelectron volts (KeV) on a planar gamma counter. Blank/empty cells indicate the measurement was not done. The value 0.00 is given to analyzed samples found to be below detection.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.4667</rdommin>
            <rdommax>38.0003</rdommax>
            <attrunit>decays per minute per gram</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>7Be_e</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A numeric identifier of the measurement error in sediment total beryllium-7 activity in decays per minute per gram (dpm/g), decay-corrected to date of core collection. Blank/empty cells indicate the measurement was not done. The value 0.00 is given to analyzed samples found to be below detection.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.0773</rdommin>
            <rdommax>7.3151</rdommax>
            <attrunit>decays per minute per gram</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>wtC</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Either total carbon or total organic carbon by weight percent in soil. Sediments in this sample set that were analyzed for both carbon content and isotopic carbon signature were not fumed prior to analysis and reported wtC is total carbon. Sediment sections without a reported isotopic signature were run in a separate lab and were fumed to remove inorganic carbon prior to analysis. Blank/empty cells indicate the measurement was not done. Refer to the attribute accuracy and process step sections for further details.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.12</rdommin>
            <rdommax>48.91</rdommax>
            <attrunit>unitless</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>wtN</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Either total nitrogen or total organic nitrogen by weight percent in soil. Sediments in this sample set that were analyzed for both nitrogen content and isotopic nitrogen signature were not fumed prior to analysis and reported wtN is total nitrogen. Sediment sections without a reported isotopic signature were run in a separate lab and were placed in an acid fuming desiccator to remove inorganics prior to analysis. Blank/empty cells indicate the measurement was not done. Refer to the attribute accuracy and process step sections for further details.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.01</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1.94</rdommax>
            <attrunit>unitless</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>13C</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The carbon isotopic signature of the soil sample relative to Pee Dee Belemnite (PDB) standard. Blank/empty cells indicate the measurement was not done.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-29.10</rdommin>
            <rdommax>-11.84</rdommax>
            <attrunit>parts per thousand OR per mil</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>15N</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The nitrogen isotopic signature of the soil sample relative to air. Blank/empty cells indicate the measurement was not done.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-1.24</rdommin>
            <rdommax>5.79</rdommax>
            <attrunit>parts per thousand OR per mil</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Age</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A numeric identifier for the age in years, from the collection date, of the core interval based on the Constant Rate of Supply excess lead-210 age model. Blank/empty cells indicate the measurement was not done.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.4</rdommin>
            <rdommax>136.2</rdommax>
            <attrunit>years</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Age_e</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A numeric identifier for the age model uncertainty, in years of the core interval, based on the Constant Rate of Supply excess lead-210 age model. Error is propagated through the model. Blank/empty cells indicate the measurement was not done.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.6</rdommin>
            <rdommax>51.8</rdommax>
            <attrunit>years</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>VAR</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Vertical Accretion Rate: A numeric identifier for the vertical accretion rate of the sediment in millimeters per year (mm/y). Calculated as the difference in interval midpoint divided by the difference in ages of those adjacent sediment intervals.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>0.8</rdommin>
            <rdommax>26.2</rdommax>
            <attrunit>millimeters per year</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>MAR</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Mass Accumulation Rate: A numeric identifier for the mass accumulation rate of the sediment in grams per square meter per year (g/m2/y). Calculated by multiplying dry bulk density times vertical accretion rate.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>163</rdommin>
            <rdommax>7858</rdommax>
            <attrunit>grams sediment per square meter per year</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CAR</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Carbon Accumulation Rate: A numeric identifier for the carbon mass accumulation rate of the sediment in grams of carbon per square meter per year (gC/m2/y). Calculated by multiplying the average mass accumulations rate for the combined depth interval of the elemental sample times weight percent carbon.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>15</rdommin>
            <rdommax>603</rdommax>
            <attrunit>grams of carbon per square meter per year</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Year</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The year corresponding to the soil horizon based on the Constant Rate of Supply excess lead-210 age model. Calculated as collection date minus age of sediment at each depth interval.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>1879.4</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2016.6</rdommax>
            <attrunit>calendar year</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Year_restored</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Calendar year corresponding to when restoration occurred.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>2001</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2010</rdommax>
            <attrunit>calendar year</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>ScienceBase</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>The dataset contains one CSV file containing the data (Data_RestoredMarsh_Cores.csv), the browse graphic, and the FGDC CSDGM metadata in XML format.</resdesc>
    <distliab>Neither the U.S. Government, the Department of the Interior, nor the USGS, nor any of their employees, contractors, or subcontractors, make any warranty, express or implied, nor assume any legal liability or responsibility for the accuracy, completeness, or usefulness of any information, apparatus, product, or process disclosed, nor represent that its use would not infringe on privately owned rights. The act of distribution shall not constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is assumed by the USGS in the use of these data or related materials. Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>CSV</formname>
          <formvern>Microsoft Excel Office 365</formvern>
          <formcont>The data release includes 1 comma separated file, a browse graphic, and the FGDC CSDGM metadata.</formcont>
          <transize>1</transize>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/file/get/60bfb987d34e86b938916dc9</networkr>
                <networkr>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/60bfb987d34e86b938916dc9</networkr>
                <networkr>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9R154DY</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
            <accinstr>The first link is to download the data in a ZIP file. The second and third links are to the landing page of the data. The last two links go to the same place; one is the DOI designation of the publication.</accinstr>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
    <techpreq>The data release includes 1 comma-delimited text file. The user must have software capable of opening the text file and reading the data formats.</techpreq>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20210630</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Jennifer A. O'Keefe Suttles</cntper>
          <cntorg>Northeast Region: WOODS HOLE COASTAL AND MARINE SCIENCE CENTER</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Chemist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>384 Woods Hole Road</address>
          <city>Woods Hole</city>
          <state>MA</state>
          <postal>02543</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>508-548-8700 x2385</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jokeefesuttles@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>
